   <Section Label="creatingPolymakeObjects"><Heading>Creating Polymake Objects</Heading>

   The interaction with the polymake program is done via files. A 
   <K>PolymakeObject</K> is mainly a pointer to a file and a list of
   known properties of the object. These properties need not be stored
   in the file. Whenever polymake is called, the returned value is
   read from standard output and stored in the <K>PolymakeObject</K>
   corresponding to the file for which polymake is called.
   
   The files for polymake are written in the old (non-xml) format.
   The first run of polymake converts them into the new (xml) format. This
   means that changes to the file by means of the methods outlined below 
   after the first run of polymake will probably lead to corrupted files.

   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="CreateEmptyFile" Arg="filename" />
     <Returns>nothing</Returns>
     <Description>
      Creates an empty file with name <A>filename</A>. Note that
      <A>filename</A> has to include the full path and the directory
      for the file must exist.
     </Description>
   </ManSection>


   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="CreatePolymakeObject" Arg=""/> 
    <Meth Name="CreatePolymakeObject" Arg="appvertyp"/> 
    <Meth Name="CreatePolymakeObject" Arg="dir"/> 
    <Meth Name="CreatePolymakeObject" Arg="dir appvertyp"/> 
    <Meth Name="CreatePolymakeObject" Arg="prefix, dir"/> 
    <Meth Name="CreatePolymakeObject" Arg="prefix dir appvertyp"/> 
    <Returns><K>PolymakeObject</K></Returns>
      <Description>

      If called without arguments, this method generates an empty file
      in the directory defined by <Ref Var="POLYMAKE_DATA_DIR"/>.

      If a directory <A>dir</A> is given (this directory must exist),
      an empty file is generated in this directory.  If <A>prefix</A>
      is not given, the file is called <F>polyN</F> where <K>N</K> is
      the current runtime. If a file of this name already exists, a
      number is appended separated by a dot (example: "poly1340" and
      "poly1340.1"). If <A>prefix</A> is given, the filename starts
      with this prefix. 

      Optionally, the file can be generated with a header specifying
      application, version and type of the object. This is done by passing the
      triple of strings <A>appvertyp</A> to 
      <Ref Meth="CreatePolymakeObject"/>. A valid triple is 
      <C>["polytope","2.3","RationalPolytope"]</C>. Validity is checked by 
      <Ref Meth="CheckAppVerTypList"/>.
    </Description>
   </ManSection>


   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="CheckAppVerTypList" Arg="appvertyp"/>
    <Returns><K>bool</K></Returns>
    <Description>
      Checks if the triple <A>arppvertyp</A> of strings specifies an
      application and type of polymake version 2.3. More specifically, the
      first entry has to be an application from 
      <C>["polytope","surface","topaz"]</C> and the third entry has to be a
      type corresponding to the application given in the first entry. The
      second entry is not checked.<Br/>
    </Description>
   </ManSection>


   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="CreatePolymakeObjectFromFile" Arg="filename"/>
    <Meth Name="CreatePolymakeObjectFromFile" Arg="dir filename"/>
    <Returns><K>PolymakeObject</K></Returns>
    <Description> 

     This method generates a <K>PolymakeObject</K> corresponding to
     the file <A>filename</A> in the directory <A>dir</A>. If
     <A>dir</A> is not given, the <K>POLYMAKE&uscore;DATA&uscore;DIR</K> is
     used.If no file with name <A>filename</A> exists in <A>dir</A> (or
     <K>POLYMAKE&uscore;DATA&uscore;DIR</K>, respectively), an empty file is created.
     
     Note that the contents of the file do not matter for the
     generation of the object. In particular, the object does not know
     any of the properties that might be encoded in the file. The only
     way to transfer information from files to <K>PolymakeObject</K>s
     is via <Ref Meth="Polymake"/>.

    </Description>
   </ManSection>

</Section>



<Section Label="accessingProperties"><Heading>Accessing Properties of Polymake Objects</Heading>

A <K>PolymakeObject</K> contains information about the directory of
its file, the name of its file and about properties calculated by
calling <Ref Meth="Polymake"/>. The properties returned by the
<K>polymake</K> program are stored under the name <K>polymake</K>
assigns to them (that is, the name of the data block in the
corresponding file).

The following methods can be used to access the information stored in
a <K>PolymakeObject</K>. But be careful! All functions return the
actual object. No copies are made. So if you change one of the
returned objects, you change the <K>PolymakeObject</K> itself.

   <ManSection> 
    <Meth Name="DirectoryOfPolymakeObject" Arg="poly"/>
     <Returns>Directory</Returns>
    <Description>
      Returns the directory of the file associated with <A>poly</A>.
    </Description>
   </ManSection>

   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="FilenameOfPolymakeObject" Arg="poly"/>
    <Returns>String</Returns>
    <Description>
    Returns the name of the file associated with <A>poly</A>. This
    does only mean the name of the <Emph>file</Emph>, not the full
    path. For the full path and file name see 
    <Ref Meth="FullFilenameOfPolymakeObject"/>
    </Description>
   </ManSection>

   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="FullFilenameOfPolymakeObject" Arg="poly"/> 
    <Returns>String</Returns>
    <Description>
    Returns the file associated with the <K>PolymakeObject</K>
    <A>poly</A> with its complete path.
    </Description>
  </ManSection>

  <ManSection>
   <Meth Name="NamesKnownPropertiesOfPolymakeObject" Arg="poly"/>
   <Returns>List of Strings</Returns>
    <Description>
    Returns a list of the names of all known properties. This does
    only include the properties returned by <Ref Meth="Polymake"/>,
    <C>"dir"</C> and <C>"filename"</C> are not included. If no
    properties are known, <K>fail</K> is returned.
   </Description>
  </ManSection>


  <ManSection>
   <Meth Name="KnownPropertiesOfPolymakeObject" Arg="poly"/>
   <Returns>Record</Returns>
    <Description>
    Returns the record of all known properties. If no
    properties are known, <K>fail</K> is returned.
   </Description>
  </ManSection>
    

  <ManSection>
   <Meth Name="PropertyOfPolymakeObject" Arg="poly name"/>
   <Description> 
   Returns the value of the property <A>name</A> if it
   is known. If the value is not known, <K>fail</K> is returned.
   <A>name</A> must be a <K>String</K>.
   </Description>
  </ManSection>

</Section>


<Section Label="Exmaple:createAndAccess">
<Heading>Example: Creating and Accessing Polymake Objects</Heading>

Suppose the file <F>/tmp/threecube.poly</F> contains the three
dimensional cube in polymake form. Now generate a
<K>PolymakeObject</K> from this file and call <Ref Meth="Polymake"/>
to make the vertices of the cube known to the object.

<Example>
<![CDATA[
### suppose we have a polymake file /tmp/threecube.poly
### containing a cube in three dimensions
gap> cube:=CreatePolymakeObjectFromFile(Directory("/tmp"),"threecube.poly");
<polymake object. No properties known>
gap> FilenameOfPolymakeObject(cube);
"threecube.poly"
gap> FullFilenameOfPolymakeObject(cube);
"/tmp/threecube.poly"
   #nothing is known about the cube:
gap> NamesKnownPropertiesOfPolymakeObject(cube);  
fail
gap> Polymake(cube,"VERTICES");
[ [ -1, -1, -1 ], [ 1, -1, -1 ], [ -1, 1, -1 ], [ 1, 1, -1 ], [ -1, -1, 1 ], 
  [ 1, -1, 1 ], [ -1, 1, 1 ], [ 1, 1, 1 ] ]  
   # Now <cube> knows its vertices:
gap> Print(cube);
<polymake object threecube.poly. Properties known: [ "VERTICES" ]>
gap> PropertyOfPolymakeObject(cube,"VERTICES");
[ [ -1, -1, -1 ], [ 1, -1, -1 ], [ -1, 1, -1 ], [ 1, 1, -1 ], [ -1, -1, 1 ],
  [ 1, -1, 1 ], [ -1, 1, 1 ], [ 1, 1, 1 ] ]
gap> KnownPropertiesOfPolymakeObject(cube);
rec(
  VERTICES := [ [ -1, -1, -1 ], [ 1, -1, -1 ], [ -1, 1, -1 ], [ 1, 1, -1 ],
      [ -1, -1, 1 ], [ 1, -1, 1 ], [ -1, 1, 1 ], [ 1, 1, 1 ] ] )
]]>
</Example>





</Section>

<Section Label="WritingToObjects">
<Heading>Writing to Polymake Objects</Heading>
   To transfer data from &GAP; to polymake, the following methods can
   be used. But bear in mind that none of these functions test if the
   resulting polymake file is still consistent.

   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="AppendToPolymakeObject" Arg="poly string"/>
    <Returns>nothing</Returns>
    <Description>
     This appends the string <A>string</A> to the file associated to
     the <K>PolymakeObject</K>
     <A>poly</A>. It is not tested if the string is syntactically
     correct as a part of a polymake file. It is also not tested if
     the string is compatible with the data already contained in the
     file.
    </Description>    
   </ManSection>

   INEQUALITIES, POINTS and VERTICES can be appended to a polymake object using
   the following functions:

   <ManSection>
   <Meth Name="AppendPointlistToPolymakeObject" Arg="poly pointlist"/>
   <Returns>nothing</Returns>
   <Description>
      Takes a list <A>pointlist</A> of vectors and converts it into a
      string which represents a polymake block labeled "POINTS". This
      string is then added to the file associated with <A>poly</A>.
      The "POINTS" block of the file associated with <A>poly</A> then
      contains points with leading ones, as polymake uses affine
      notation.
   </Description>
   </ManSection>

   <ManSection>
   <Meth Name="AppendVertexlistToPolymakeObject" Arg="poly pointlist"/>
   <Returns>nothing</Returns>
   <Description>
      Does the same as <C>AppendPointlistToPolymakeObject</C>, but with
      "VERTICES" instead of "POINTS".
   </Description>
   </ManSection>

   <ManSection>
   <Meth Name="AppendInequalitiesToPolymakeObject" Arg="poly ineqlist"/>
   <Returns>nothing</Returns>
   <Description>
     Just appends the inequalities given in <A>ineqlist</A> to  the polymake
     object <A> poly</A> (with caption "INEQUALITIES"). Note that this does 
     not check if an "INEQUALITIES" section does already exist in the file 
     associated with <A>poly</A>.
   </Description>
   </ManSection>


  <ManSection>
   <Meth  Name="ConvertMatrixToPolymakeString" Arg="name matrix"/>
   <Returns>String</Returns>
   <Description>
    This function takes a matrix <A>matrix</A> and converts it to a
    string. This string can then be appended to a polymake file via
    <Ref Meth="AppendToPolymakeObject"/> to form a block of data labeled
    <A>name</A>.

    This may be used to write blocks like INEQUALITIES or FACETS.
   </Description>
   </ManSection>

   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="ClearPolymakeObject" Arg="poly"/>
    <Meth Name="ClearPolymakeObject" Arg="poly appvertyp"/>
    <Returns>nothing</Returns>
    <Description>
     Deletes all known properties of the <K>PolymakeObject</K>
     <A>poly</A> and replaces its file with an empty one.
     <Br/>
     If the triple of strings <A>appvertyp</A> specifying application, version
     and type (see <Ref Meth="CheckAppVerTypList"/>) is given, the file is
     replaced with a file that contains only a header specifying application,
     version and type of the polymake object.
    </Description>
   </ManSection>
   
   There are also methods to manipulate the known values without
   touching the file of the <K>PolymakeObject</K>:

   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="WriteKnownPropertyToPolymakeObject" Arg="poly name data"/>
    <Description>
     Takes the object <A>data</A> and writes it to the known
     properties section of the <K>PolymakeObject</K> <A>poly</A>. The
     string <A>name</A> is used as the name of the property. If a
     property with that name already exists, it is overwritten.
     Again, there is no check if <A>data</A> is consistent, correct or
     meaningful.
    </Description>
   </ManSection>

   <ManSection>
    <Meth Name="UnbindKnownPropertyOfPolymakeObject" Arg="poly name"/>

    <Description>
     If the <K>PolymakeObject</K> <A>poly</A> has a property with name
     <A>name</A>, that property is unbound. If there is no such
     property, <K>fail</K> is returned.
    </Description>
   </ManSection>   

</Section>

